<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<publicwhip>

<spmotion spid="S3M-5075" date="2009-10-29" filename="day-bb-09_bb-10-29f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-09/bb-10-29f.htm">
*S3M-5075 Ian McKee: Loanhead Town Hall—That the Parliament notes with disappointment the decision of Midlothian Council to demolish Loanhead town hall; believes that this decision was taken in the face of strong local opposition and with no public consultation; commends the efforts of the community in Loanhead in trying to save its town hall, and encourages Midlothian Council to reconsider its decision in order to allow the community time to come forward with plans to take over the running of the town hall. 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-5075" date="2009-10-30" filename="day-bb-09_bb-10-30f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-09/bb-10-30f.htm">
 S3M-5075 Loanhead Town Hall (lodged on 28 October 2009) Rob Gibson*, Alasdair Allan*, Bill Kidd*, Aileen Campbell*, Shirley-Anne Somerville*, Robin Harper* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-5075" date="2009-11-02" filename="day-bb-09_bb-11-02f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-09/bb-11-02f.htm">
S3M-5075 Ian McKee: Loanhead Town Hall—That the Parliament notes with disappointment the decision of Midlothian Council to demolish Loanhead town hall; believes that this decision was taken in the face of strong local opposition and with no public consultation; commends the efforts of the community in Loanhead in trying to save its town hall, and encourages Midlothian Council to reconsider its decision in order to allow the community time to come forward with plans to take over the running of the town hall. Supported by: Rob Gibson, Alasdair Allan, Bill Kidd, Aileen Campbell, Shirley-Anne Somerville, Robin Harper, Rhona Brankin*, Angela Constance* 
</spmotion>

<spmotion spid="S3M-5075" date="2009-11-06" filename="day-bb-09_bb-11-06f.htm" url="http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/business/businessBulletin/bb-09/bb-11-06f.htm">
 S3M-5075 Loanhead Town Hall (lodged on 28 October 2009) Gil Paterson* 
</spmotion>

</publicwhip>
